Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Additional Records 5646
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Additional Records
1962-1971
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
5646
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Records of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen ad speeches by its president, H. E. Gilbert.
5685194
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, July 18, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, July 18, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen was founded on December 1, 1873 in Port Jervis, New York by Erie Railroad firemen in order to provide mutual support for railroad firemen. Their first convention was in 1874, at which they adopted their first constitution. The Brotherhood initially emphasized insurance, but by the late nineteenth century had branched out into labor-management relations.
In 1907, the organization changed its name to the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen [BLF&E], reflecting the changes in its membership as former firemen were promoted to engineers and permitting locomotive engineers to join its ranks. In 1969, the union merged with the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, and the Switchmen's Union of North America to form the United Transportation Union.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1962-1971
Bulk dates: 1967-1971
This collection contains select records from the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Engineers [BLF&E] and eleven speeches from BLF&E President H. E. Gilbert. The records are from the early 1960s and document the struggle faced by locomotive firemen, also known as helpers, as their positions on locomotive crews were being eliminated.
The bulk of the collection consists of the speeches of H. E. Gilbert and are all concerned with the merger of the BLF&E with the Order of Railroad Conductors and Brakemen, the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, and the Switchmen's Union of North America that created the United Transportation Union. The speeches advocate for the merger, defend the need for the merger, discuss what steps have been taken to create the UTU, and then reflect back on the successes of the merger and areas for improvement that the UTU leadership will address.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5141: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Records 5141 G: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Graphics 5141 MB: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Memorabilia 5176: Grand Lodge of the Ladies Society of the Former Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Records 5467: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Local 807 (Auburn, NY) Records 5475: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen General Chairman, Boston and Maine Railroad Records 5611: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Honorary Register of Disabled 5869: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Local 807 (Auburn, NY) Additional Records 6176: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Additional Records
Labor unions -- Mergers -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial.; Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Gilbert, H. E.; United Transportation Union; Erie-Lackawanna Railroad
5685194
- Erie-Lackawanna Employees Mass Meeting Poster, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  "General Chairmen and Top Officers of All Railroad Labor Unions, Representing E&L Employees were Requested to be at This Highly Important Meeting" (includes list of local chairmen of various railroad unions)
- Emergency Board No.154: Report to the President, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Interdivisional Runs: Conferences, mediation, correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Interdivisional Runs: Employees Protections, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- H. E. Gilbert Speech no.16: At School of Law, University of Kansas, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5a)
- H. E. Gilbert Speech no.17: Unity: The Key to the Secure Future, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5b)
  Advocating for unification and the formation of UTU
- H. E. Gilbert Speech no.18: At the SUNA 8th Quadrennial Convention., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Advocating for unification and creation of UTU
- H. E. Gilbert Speech no.19: At the BLF&E 39th Convention, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Includes full copy of Enginemen's Press, vol. 10, No. 24, in which the speech is printed.
- H. E. Gilbert Speech no.20: At the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Convention, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- H. E. Gilbert Speech no.21: At St. Louis, MO Seminar, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Seminar to train union officers and members for service in UTU
- H. E. Gilbert Speech no.22: At the Eugene V. Debs Awards Banquet, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Acceptance speech by Mr. Gilbert for winning the Debs' Award
- H. E. Gilbert Speech no.23: What Is Right With the UTU, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- H. E. Gilbert Speech no.24: Resolution of the Manning Issue, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Given at a collective bargaining seminar, New York City, on the crew consist of diesel engines.
- H. E. Gilbert Speech no.25: What Are Our Standards?, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13a)
  Given at Dixie Boosters Meeting of the UTU
- H. E. Gilbert Speech no.26: Unification - What Was Our Purpose?, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13b)
  Given at Lexington, Kentucky.